Christopher S. Meiklejohn

christopher.meiklejohn@gmail.com 50 Elite Drive, Warwick, RI, 02889 http://www.christophermeiklejohn.com

PROFILE

Functional programmer, distributed systems researcher, conference speaker, and open source contributor.

INTERESTS

Conflict-Free Replicated Data Types (CRDTs)

Applications of CRDTs in distributed systems, specifically partitioned and replicated computation in large-scale systems.

Distributed Computing

Efficient distributed computation in mobile and desktop applications supporting offline operation that preserve the correctness properties of applications.

Education

Instruction of distributed systems topics.

PUBLICATIONS Meiklejohn, C., and Van Rov, P. (2015)

Lasp: a language for distributed, eventually consistent computations with CRDTs In Proceedings of the First Workshop on Principles and Practice of Consistency for Distributed Data (PaPoC '15)

Collocated with EuroSys '15; April 21, 2015; Bordeaux, FR

Meiklejohn, C. (2014)

Augmented Inverted Indexes to Track Causality in Eventually Consistent Data Stores Middleware '14 Poster Session

December 8-12 2014; Bordeaux, FR

Meiklejohn, C. (2014)

Eventual Consistency and Deterministic Dataflow Programming

A Case Study of Integrating Derflow with the Riak Data Store.

LADIS '14: 8th Workshop on Large-Scale Distributed Systems and Middleware October 23-24, 2014; Cambridge, UK

Bravo, M., Li, Z., Van Roy, P., and Meiklejohn, C. (2014)

Derflow: distributed deterministic dataflow programming for erlang

In Proceedings of the Thirteenth ACM SIGPLAN workshop on Erlang (Erlang '14) Collocated with ICFP '14; September 5, 2014; Goteborg, Sweden

Brown, R., Cribbs, S., Meiklejohn, C., Elliott, S. (2014)

Riak DT map: a composable, convergent replicated dictionary.

In Proceedings of the First Workshop on Principles and Practice of Eventual Consistency (PaPEC '14)

Collocated with EuroSys '14; April 13, 2014; Amsterdam, NL

Meiklejohn, C. (2014)

On the composability of the Riak DT map:

Expanding from embedded to multi-key structures.

In Proceedings of the First Workshop on Principles and Practice of Eventual Consistency (PaPEC '14)

Collocated with EuroSys '14; April 13, 2014; Amsterdam, NL

Meiklejohn, C., (2013)

Riak PG: Distributed Process Groups on Dynamo-style Distributed Storage In Proceedings of the twelfth ACM SIGPLAN workshop on Erlang (Erlang '13) Collocated with ICFP '13; September 28, 2013; Boston, MA

EDUCATION Graduate Coursework, Computer Science

Brown University, Providence, RI

One semester of coursework completed.

Bachelor of Science, Information Technology

2006 - 2009

2013

Northeastern University, Boston, MA,

G.P.A. 3.75/4.0, Summa Cum Laude, Sigma Epsilon Rho Honor Society Member

Associate of Science, Computer Science

2001 - 2006

Community College of Rhode Island, Warwick, RI

TALKS / ARTICLES

Highly Distributed Computations Without Synchronization InfoQ, February 17th, 2015

 $Functional\ Web\ Apps\ with\ Webmachine$

BOBkonf 2015; Berlin, Germany

Introduction to Riak

BOBkonf 2015; Berlin, Germany

Building Applications with Distributed Erlang

NDC London 2014; London, United Kingdom

Eventually Consistent Computations ReactConf 2014; San Francisco, CA

Eventually Consistent Computation with CRDTs

RICON 2014; Las Vegas, NV

SyncFree: Large-Scale Computation Without Synchronization

RICON 2014; Las Vegas, NV

Eventual Consistency and Deterministic Dataflow Programming

LADIS Workshop '14; Cambridge, UK

"A Note On Distributed Computing" (1994)

Papers We Love 2014; Boston, MA

Derflow: Distributed Deterministic Dataflow Programming

ACM SIGPLAN Erlang Workshop 2014; Gothenburg, Sweden

Distributed deterministic dataflow programming for Erlang

Erlang User Conference 2014; Stockholm, Sweden

Convergent / Divergent

EmberConf 2014; Portland, OR

On The Composability of the Riak DT Map:

Expanding From Embedded To Multi-Key Structures

PaPEC 2014; Amsterdam, NL

Verified Vector Clocks: An Unexpected Journey

Erlang Factory 2014, San Francisco; San Francisco, CA

Verified Vector Clocks RICON West 2013; San Francisco, CA

Riak PG: Distributed Process Groups on Dynamo-style Distributed Storage ACM SIGPLAN Erlang Workshop 2013; Boston, MA

Choose Your Own Consistency Toronto Erlang Factory Lite 2013; Toronto, ON

Bloom: A Language For Disorderly Distributed Computing Wicked Good Ruby 2013; Boston, MA

What Even Is An Erlang? Wicked Good Ruby 2013 Lightning Talk; Boston, MA

Functional Web Apps with Webmachine LambdaJam 2013; Chicago, IL

Implementing a Distributed Process Registry on Riak Core New York Erlang Factory Lite 2013; New York, NY

From Ruby to Erlang: An Unexpected Journey Chicago Erlang Factory Lite 2013; Chicago, IL

An Introduction to Functional Reactive Programming NodePDX 2013; Portland, OR

Distributed Data Structures in Coq RICON East 2013; New York, NY

Building Ambitious Web Applications with Ember.JS FITC 2012; Waltham, MA

AWARDS

Academic Excellence Award, Northeastern University, 2009
Awarded to students with the highest grade point average in their field of study.

BRASS Award, Berklee College of Music, 2008 Awarded to outstanding employees during the fiscal year.

Zero Hero Award, Conversent Communication, 2006 Awarded to employees for zero customer loss.

EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer

March 2012 - Present

Basho Technologies, Inc., Cambridge, MA

- Responsible for research on CRDTs under our partnership with SyncFree.
- Worked on Basho's replicated data center product, optimizing performance and reliability of multi-datacenter replication.
- Responsible for building out an application to manage usage of a half-petabyte object store using Ruby, JavaScript and D3.
- Developed closed-source web utilities for managing access to product trials.
- Implemented open-source client libraries for Riak CS in Ruby and Erlang.

Contributor and Maintainer

July 2011 - Present

Rubygems.org (Community-hosted Ruby packages)

• Assisted in maintenance and development of the rubygems.org platform.

Software Engineer

November 2010 - March 2012

Swipely, Inc., Providence, RI

- Responsible for developing the Swipely platform, which is written in Rails 3 using RDS, MongoDB and Riak.
- Created a dynamic newsfeed based on purchasing history of customers, that prioritized scheduling based on purchase history and frequency.
- Introduced team to pair programming, test and behavior driven development.

• Took the lead on migrating our infrastructure from Rails 2.3.4 to Rails 3.0+.

- Contributed patches to Rails core, and various open source libraries.

Volunteer Systems Administrator

May 2010 - March 2012

Devio.us (Free OpenBSD Shell Provider)

• Assisted in all operational upgrades of Devio.us systems and user management.

Lead Software Developer

February 2010 - July 2010

Tapchamp, LLC.

- Developed Rails-based fantasy play prediction system, which included Facebook integration and mobile API for iPhone application.
- Deployed and managed all servers responsible for platform.

South End Community Health Center, Boston, MA

2010

Working with a designer to build English and Spanish versions of their website.

Coevolution Interactive, Boston, MA

2009 - 2010

• Provided e-commerce and web development work for various clients.

Crunchy Granola Baby, LLC., Salem, MA

2008 - 2009

• Designed and implemented e-commerce solution for their online store.

Web Programmer and Systems Administrator August 2008 - February 2009 Artists House Music, New Orleans, LA

- Designed and implemented custom solutions to support marketing initiatives.
- Provided systems support to staff, as well as general systems administration services.

Software Engineering Manager and Systems Engineer April 2008 - October 2010 Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA

- Managed software development for the Berklee Media business division.
- Responsible for ensuring 24/7 uptime of all systems, rapid response to critical issues and delivering custom software products.
- Worked with the CTO and the Software Engineering Managers from other divisions to ensure applications are being developed following the proper standards.
- Configured and maintained hardware at two data center facilities as well as provisioned a disaster recovery site.

Software Developer and Systems Engineer Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA

July 2006 - April 2008

- Developed for, and supported, custom AOLServer/OpenACS installations.
- Designed and supported web solutions using PHP, TCL, XML/XPATH, and Smarty.
- Provided 24/7 support for web services.

Senior Systems Engineer

January 2005 - July 2006

Conversent Communications, Lincoln, RI

- Designed and implemented high availability solutions for e-mail and web systems.
- Implemented a multi-server LDAP infrastructure.
- Worked in their data center to provide installation and support for customers.
- Designed and deployed an auto-provisioning system to integrate with their OSS.
- Designed database-driven systems for tracking data center customers and billing burstable bandwidth customers.

Systems Engineer

January 2000 - January 2005

Conversent Communications, Warwick, RI

- Worked in a small team to develop, maintain and deploy low-cost solutions for data products.
- Deployed Linux, Solaris, Windows and FreeBSD based systems.
- Designed database-driven web-based solutions for customer management in Perl, Java, and PHP.

Technical Support/Customer Service

August 1998 - June 2000

IDS World Network, East Greenwich, RI

• Provided technical support and customer service via telephone, e-mail and news-group for customers.

COMMUNITY

Program Committees

Participated in program committees.

- Member of the ACM SIGPLAN Erlang Workshop 2015 PC.
- Member of the ACM DEBS 2015 Industry PC.
- Member of the ACM EuroSys 2014 shadow PC.

Events and User Groups

Assisted in the organization of several commerically and community supported events and user groups.

- Co-organized Curry On Prague! 2015.
- Attended the 2013 Oregon Programming Languages Summer School.
- Organized DowncityJS, a hackathon in Providence, RI.
- Assisted in organizing the RICON conference for the past three years.
- Functional Programmers; Providence, RI
- Ember.JS; Boston, MA

Think Distributed

Creator and host of the Think Distributed podcast, focusing on making distributed systems understandable.

- Hosted episodes featuring various researchers and practitioners.
- Held live panel discussions at Strange Loop 2013 and RICON 2013/2014.

SyncFree Consortium

Contributing member and industry partner of the SyncFree research project on largescale syncronization-free computation funded by the European Union under the Seventh Framework Programme.

- Worked with Universite catholique de Louvain on building a programming model for working with eventual consistency.
- Assisted in the development and testing of the projects reference platform.
- Built out testing infrastructure for the reference platform for repeatable executions of test code and use case simulation.